<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' []>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-sidrops-prefer-rrdp-01" updates="6841, 8182">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc private=""?>
<?rfc topblock="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<front>
<title abbrev="RPKI Repository Requirements">Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) Repository Requirements</title>

<author initials="T." surname="Bruijnzeels" fullname="Tim Bruijnzeels">
<organization>NLnet Labs</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<code></code>
<country></country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>tim@nlnetlabs.nl</email>
<uri>https://www.nlnetlabs.nl/</uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="R." surname="Bush" fullname="Randy Bush">
<organization>Internet Initiative Japan &amp; Arrcus, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<code></code>
<country></country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>randy@psg.com</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="G." surname="Michaelson" fullname="George Michaelson">
<organization>APNIC</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<code></code>
<country></country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>ggm@apnic.net</email>
<uri>http://www.apnic.net</uri>
</address>
</author>
<date year="2021" month="September" day="27"/>

<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup></workgroup>


<abstract>
<t>This document formulates a plan of a phased transition to a state where
RPKI repositories and Relying Party software performing RPKI Validation
will use the RPKI Repository Delta Protocol (RRDP) <xref target="RFC8182"/> as the
preferred access protocol, and require rsync as a fallback option only.
</t>
<t>In phase 0, today's deployment, RRDP is supported by most, but not all
Repositories, and most but not all RP software.
</t>
<t>In the proposed phase 1 RRDP will become mandatory to implement for
Repositories, in addition to rsync. This phase can start as soon as
this document is published.
</t>
<t>Once the proposed updates are implemented by all Repositories phase 2
will start. In this phase RRDP will become mandatory to implement for
all RP software, and rsync will be required as a fallback option only.
</t>
<t>It should be noted that although this document currently includes
descriptions and updates to RFCs for each of these phases, we may find
that it will be beneficial to have one or more separate documents for
these phases, so that it might be more clear to all when the updates
to RFCs take effect.
</t>
</abstract>


</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="requirements-notation" title="Requirements notation">
<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;, &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;,
&quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;NOT RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in
this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
<xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="motivation" title="Motivation">
<t>The Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) <xref target="RFC6480"/> as originally defined
uses rsync as its distribution protocol, as outlined in <xref target="RFC6481"/>. Later, the
RPKI Repository Delta Protocol (RRDP) <xref target="RFC8182"/> was designed to provide an
alternative. In order to facilitate incremental deployment RRDP has been
deployed as an additional optional protocol, while rsync was still mandatory to
implement.
</t>
<t>While rsync has been very useful in the initial deployment of RPKI, a number of
issues observed with it motivated the design of RRDP, e.g.:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>rsync is CPU and memory heavy on the server side, and easy to DoS</t>
<t>rsync library support is lacking, complicating RP efficiency and error logging</t>
<t>we cannot ensure that RPs get atomic sets of updated objects</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>RRDP was designed to leverage HTTPS CDN infrastructure to provide RPKI Repository
content in a resilient way, while reducing the load on the Repository server. It
supports that updates are published as atomic deltas, which can help prevent
most of the issues described in section 6 of <xref target="RFC6486"/>.
</t>
<t>For a longer discussion please see section 1 of <xref target="RFC8182"/>.
</t>
<t>In conclusion: we believe that while RRDP is not perfect, and we may indeed
need future work to improve on it, it is an improvement over using rsync in the
context of RPKI. Therefore, this document outlines a transition plan where RRDP
becomes mandatory to implement, and the operational dependency on rsync is
reduced to that of a fallback option.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="plan-to-prefer-rrdp" title="Plan to prefer RRDP">
<t>Changing the RPKI infrastructure to rely on RRDP instead of rsync is a delicate
operation. There is current deployment of Certification Authorities, Repository
Servers and Relying Party software which relies on rsync, and which may not yet
support RRDP.
</t>
<t>Therefore we need to have a plan that ultimately updates the relevant RFCs, but
which uses a phased approach combined with measurements to limit the operational
impact of doing this to (almost) zero.
</t>
<t>The general outline of the plan is as follows. We will describe each step in
more detail below.
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="center">Phase</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">Description</ttcol>

<c>0</c><c>RPKI repositories support rsync, and optionally RRDP</c>
<c>1</c><c>RPKI repositories support both rsync and RRDP</c>
<c>2</c><c>All RP software prefers RRDP</c>
</texttable>

<section anchor="phase-0--rpki-repositories-support-rsync-and-optionally-rrdp" title="Phase 0 - RPKI repositories support rsync, and optionally RRDP">
<t>This is the situation at the time of writing this document. Relying Parties can
prefer RRDP over rsync today, but they need to support rsync until all RPKI
repositories support RRDP. Therefore all repositories should support RRDP at
their earliest convenience.
</t>

<section anchor="updates-to-rfc-8182" title="Updates to RFC 8182">
<t>Repositories which support RRDP MUST ensure that RRDP resources are available
to Relying Parties (section 3.3 of <xref target="RFC8182"/>). Furthermore, the RRDP repository
MUST include all current repository objects. Because of this the choice of
falling back to alternative repository access mechanisms was left as a local
policy choice of RP software.
</t>
<t>However, following discussions on this subject it has become clear that there is
a preference to instruct RP software to make use of all possible data sources.
The main motivation being that because of RPKI object security using a secondary
source of data can never lead to a worse outcome in terms of validation.
</t>
<t>The following update is therefore applicable to section 3.4.5 &quot;Considerations
Regarding Operational Failures in RRDP&quot; of <xref target="RFC8182"/>:
</t>
<t>OLD:
   Relying Parties could attempt to use alternative repository access
   mechanisms, if they are available, according to the accessMethod
   element value(s) specified in the SIA of the associated certificate
   (see Section 4.8.8 of [RFC6487]).
</t>
<t>NEW:
   Relying Parties MUST attempt to use alternative repository access
   mechanisms, if they are available, according to the accessMethod
   element value(s) specified in the SIA of the associated certificate
   (see Section 4.8.8 of [RFC6487]).
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="updates-to-rfc-6481" title="Updates to RFC 6481">
<t>As noted above section 3.3 of <xref target="RFC8182"/> already stipulates that RRDP
files MUST be made available by repositories which support RRDP. In other
words the RRDP service must be treated as a critical service wherever it
is supported.
</t>
<t>During this phase the updates are applied to section 3 of <xref target="RFC6481"/>, to
make this abundantly clear:
</t>
<t>OLD:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>The publication repository SHOULD be hosted on a highly
available service and high-capacity publication platform.</t>
<t>The publication repository MUST be available using rsync
<xref target="RFC5781"/> [RSYNC]. Support of additional retrieval mechanisms
is the choice of the repository operator.  The supported
retrieval mechanisms MUST be consistent with the accessMethod
element value(s) specified in the SIA of the associated CA or
EE certificate.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>NEW:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>The publication repository MAY be available using the RPKI
Repository Delta Protocol <xref target="RFC8182"/>. If RPDP is provided,
it SHOULD be hosted on a highly available platform.</t>
<t>The publication repository MUST be available using rsync
<xref target="RFC5781"/> [RSYNC]. The rsync server SHOULD be hosted on a
highly available platform.</t>
<t>Support of additional retrieval mechanisms is the choice of the repository
operator. The supported retrieval mechanisms MUST be consistent with the
accessMethod element value(s) specified in the SIA of the associated CA or
EE certificate.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="phase-1--rpki-repositories-support-both-rsync-and-rrdp" title="Phase 1 - RPKI repositories support both rsync and RRDP">
<t>During this phase we will make RRDP mandatory to support for Repository Servers,
and measure whether the deployed Repository Servers have been upgraded to do so,
in as far as they don't support RRDP already.
</t>

<section anchor="updates-to-rfc-6481-1" title="Updates to RFC 6481">
<t>During this phase the updates are applied to section 3 of <xref target="RFC6481"/>.
</t>
<t>OLD:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>The publication repository SHOULD be hosted on a highly
available service and high-capacity publication platform.</t>
<t>The publication repository MUST be available using rsync
<xref target="RFC5781"/> [RSYNC]. Support of additional retrieval mechanisms
is the choice of the repository operator.  The supported
retrieval mechanisms MUST be consistent with the accessMethod
element value(s) specified in the SIA of the associated CA or
EE certificate.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>NEW:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>The publication repository MUST be available using the RPKI
Repository Delta Protocol <xref target="RFC8182"/>. The RRDP server SHOULD
be hosted on a highly available platform.</t>
<t>The publication repository MUST be available using rsync
<xref target="RFC5781"/> [RSYNC]. The rsync server SHOULD be hosted on a
highly available platform.</t>
<t>Support of additional retrieval mechanisms is the choice of the repository
operator. The supported retrieval mechanisms MUST be consistent with the
accessMethod element value(s) specified in the SIA of the associated CA or
EE certificate.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="measurements" title="Measurements">
<t>We can find out whether all RPKI repositories support RRDP by running (possibly)
modified Relying Party software that keeps track of this.
</t>
<t>When it is found that Repositories do not yet support RRDP, outreach should be
done to them individually. Since the number of Repositories is fairly low, and
it is in their interest to run RRDP because it addresses availability concerns,
we have confidence that we will find these Repositories willing to make changes.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="phase-2--all-rp-software-prefers-rrdp" title="Phase 2 - All RP software prefers RRDP">
<t>Once all Repositories support RRDP we can proceed to make RRDP mandatory to
implement for Relying Party software. But note that RP software is not prohibited
from implementing this support sooner. At the time of this writing all know
RP software supports RRDP, although it is not known to the authors whether all
of them have RRDP enabled and use it as the preferred protocol.
</t>

<section anchor="updates-to-rfc-8182-1" title="Updates to RFC 8182">
<t>From this phase onwards the updates are applied to section 3.4.1 of <xref target="RFC8182"/>.
</t>
<t>OLD:
  When a Relying Party performs RPKI validation and learns about a
  valid certificate with an SIA entry for the RRDP protocol, it SHOULD
  use this protocol as follows.
</t>
<t>NEW:
  When a Relying Party performs RPKI validation and learns about a
  valid certificate with an SIA entry for the RRDP protocol, it MUST
  use this protocol with preference.
</t>
<t>Relying Parties MUST NOT attempt to fetch objects using alternate access mechanisms, if object retrieval through this protocol is successful.
</t>
<t>However, as stipulated in section 3.4.5, Relying Parties MUST attempt to
  use alternative repository access mechanisms, if object retrieval through
  this protocol is unsuccessful.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="measurements-1" title="Measurements">
<t>Although the tools may support RRDP, users will still need to install updated
versions of these tools in their infrastructure. Any Repository operator can
measure this transition by observing access to their RRDP and rsync repositories
respectively.
</t>
<t>But even after new versions have been available, it is expected that there will
be a long, low volume, tail of users who did not upgrade and still depend on rsync.
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="appendix--implementation-status" title="Appendix - Implementation Status">
<t>Note that this section is included for tracking purposes during the discussion
phase of this document and is not intended to be included in an RFC.
</t>

<section anchor="current-rrdp-support-in-repository-software" title="Current RRDP Support in Repository Software">
<t>The currently known support for RRDP for repositories is as follows:
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="center">Repository Implementation</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">Support for RRDP</ttcol>

<c>afrinic</c><c>yes</c>
<c>apnic</c><c>yes</c>
<c>arin</c><c>yes</c>
<c>lacnic</c><c>ongoing</c>
<c>ripe ncc</c><c>yes</c>
<c>Dragon Research Labs</c><c>yes(1,2)</c>
<c>krill</c><c>yes(1)</c>
</texttable>
<t>(1) in use at various National Internet Registries, as well as other resource
    holders under RIRs.
(2) not all organizations using this software have upgraded to using RRDP.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="current-rrdp-support-in-relying-party-software" title="Current RRDP Support in Relying Party software">
<t>All current versions of known Relying Party software support RRDP:
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="center">Relying Party Implementation</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">support</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">version</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">since</ttcol>

<c>FORT</c><c>yes</c><c>1.2.0</c><c>02/2021</c>
<c>OctoRPKI</c><c>yes</c><c>1.0.0</c><c>02/2019</c>
<c>rcynic</c><c>yes</c><c>?</c><c>?</c>
<c>Routinator</c><c>yes</c><c>0.6.0</c><c>09/2019</c>
<c>rpki-client</c><c>yes</c><c>0.7.0</c><c>04/2021</c>
<c>RPSTIR2</c><c>yes</c><c>2.0</c><c>04/2020</c>
</texttable>
<t>But, support for RRDP does not necessarily mean that it is also
enabled and preferred over rsync by default. The authors kindly
request that RP implementors provide the following information:
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="center">Relying Party Implementation</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">prefer</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">version</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">since</ttcol>

<c>FORT</c><c>yes</c><c>?</c><c>?</c>
<c>OctoRPKI</c><c>?</c><c>?</c><c>?</c>
<c>rcynic</c><c>?</c><c>?</c><c>?</c>
<c>Routinator</c><c>yes</c><c>0.6.0</c><c>09/2019</c>
<c>rpki-client</c><c>?</c><c>?</c><c>?</c>
<c>RPSTIR2</c><c>?</c><c>?</c><c>?</c>
</texttable>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>This document has no IANA actions.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
<t>TBD
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
<t>TBD
</t>
</section>

</middle>
<back>
<references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5781.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6480.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6481.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6486.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8182.xml"?>
</references>

</back>
</rfc>
